Guide to the Gail Shibley collection
Oregon Historical Society Research Library
Gail Shibley collection
1990-2007
Oregon Historical Society Research Library
Shibley, Gail R.
Coll 285
0.9 cubic feet 2 document cases
Collection of photographs, clippings, ephemera, and related materials documenting the career of Gail Shibley, who worked in local, state, and federal government, and was the first openly LGBTQ person to serve in the Oregon State Legislature.
Collection is open for research.
Gift of Gail R. Shibley, September 2011 (Lib. Acc. 27437).
The collection is arranged in two series: Series 1, Papers; Series 2, Photographs.
A native of Oregon, Gail Shibley was educated at the University of Oregon, Harvard University, and the Lewis and Clark Law School, where she received her law degree in 2009. She served on the staff of U.S. Representative Jim Weaver of Oregon from 1980-1986, was the program manager of the city of Portland's Bureau of Traffic Management from 1990-1996, and was elected to the Oregon House of Representatives in 1991, where she served until 1997 -- the first openly LGBTQ person to serve in the state Legislature. After an unsuccessful campaign for Portland City Council in 1996, she served as the development director of LINK CDC in Portland from 1997-1998, the director of external communications at the Federal Highway Administration from 1998-2000, was the senior advisor to the secretary of labor from 2000-2001, international liaison for the Saxony Parliament in Germany from 2001-2002, and was the political director of John Kulongoski's campaign for Oregon governor in 2001-2002. Shen then served as the administrator of Environmental Public Health for the state of Oregon, and in 2013 became chief of staff for Portland Mayor Charlie Hales. She returned to state government in 2015, serving as assistant director for business services at the Oregon Youth Authority, and retired in 2017.
The collection contains photographs, clippings, ephemera, and related materials documenting Gail Shibley's public career through 2007. Most of the collection relates to her election campaigns and her years in the Oregon State Legislature. Included are photographs of Shibley with Oregon Governor Barbara Roberts.
Video recordings received with this collection were separated to moving image collections at the Oregon Historical Society Research Library.
Shibley, Gail R.--Photographs; Roberts, Barbara, 1936---Photographs
Oregon. Legislative Assembly. House of Representatives
Oregon--Politics and government--1951-
Lesbians--Oregon; Gay legislators--Oregon; Gay legislators--Oregon--Photographs; Legislators--Oregon; Legislators--Oregon--Photographs; Political campaigns--Oregon; Gay rights--Oregon
Photographs; Oregon; Gays and Lesbians; Politics and Politicians
clippings (information artifacts); printed ephemera; photographs
- Papers, 1990-2007; Series 1
  - Biographical--resume of Gail Shibley, circa 2004 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Campaign clippings, 1991-1996 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Campaign ephemera--flyers, advertisements, etc., circa 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Campaign Plan", 1992 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Child care, health care"--clippings, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Christopher Street magazine interview with Shibley, 1992 July 21 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Conference of local health officials--public health emergency preparedness leadership team", 2007 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Gay and lesbian issues"--clippings, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - General clippings, 1991-1996 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - House of Representatives appointment--clippings, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - "Legislative process"--clippings, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "Measure 9 and OCA [Oregon Citizens Alliance]"--clippings, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Taxes and state budget"--clippings, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Transportation"--clippings and news release, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Photographs, 1990-2000; Series 2
  - Announcement to run for office, 1991 October (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - At desk in legislative offices, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bicycle, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Campaign appearance, Portland--contact sheets and negatives, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Campaign--contact sheets, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Campaign--negatives, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Constituent involvement", circa 1990-1994 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Contact sheets, general, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Election victory--photos by Linda Clark, 1992 November (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Full-posed portraits of Shibley, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Giving speeches, circa 1990-1994 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Head shots, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - In the legislative chamber, circa 1991-1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Interview on unidentified talk show, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Linda Kliewer photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Miscellaneous photographs of Shibley, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Portland scenes by Anne Weaver, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Portraits of Shibley by Lisa Currier--contact sheets, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Town hall meetings, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Includes images of Shibley with Portland mayor Vera Katz.
  - White House group portrait, with President Bill Clinton, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - With Oregon Governor Barbara Roberts, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)